<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "/usr/share/xml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="ch_wireless">
<title>Wireless Networking</title>

<section id="wireless_iwconfig">
  <title>
    <application>iwconfig</application>
  </title>

<para>
Wireless networking is somewhat more complicated than traditional wired
networking, and requires additional tools for setup. Slackware includes
a diverse collection of wireless networking tools to allow you to
configure your wireless network interface card &#40;WNIC&#41; at the most basic
level. We won't cover everything here, but should give you a solid
foundation to get up and running quickly.  The first tool we are going
to look at is <application>iwconfig</application>(8). When run without
any argument, <application>iwconfig</application> displays the current
wireless information on any and all NICs on your computer.
</para>

<screen><prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>iwconfig</userinput>
lo        no wireless extensions.

eth0      no wireless extensions.

wmaster0  no wireless extensions.

wlan0     IEEE 802.11abgn  ESSID:"nest"  
          Mode:Managed  Frequency:2.432 GHz  Access Point:
00:13:10:EA:4E:BD   
          Bit Rate=54 Mb&#47;s   Tx-Power=17 dBm   
          Retry min limit:7   RTS thr:off   Fragment thr=2352 B   
          Encryption key:off
          Power Management:off
          Link Quality=100&#47;100  Signal level:-42 dBm  
          Rx invalid nwid:0  Rx invalid crypt:0  Rx invalid frag:0
          Tx excessive retries:0  Invalid misc:0   Missed beacon:0

tun0      no wireless extensions.
</screen>

<para>
Unlike wired networks, wireless networks are &#34;fuzzy&#34;. Their borders are
hard to define, and multiple networks may overlap one another. In order
to avoid confusion, each wireless network has &#40;hopefully&#41; unique
identifiers. The two most basic identifiers are the Extended Service
Set Identifier &#40;ESSID&#41; and the channel or frequency for radio
transmission. The ESSID is simply a name that identifies the wireless
network in question; you may have heard it referred to as the &#34;network
name&#34; or something similar. 
</para>

<para> 
Typical wireless networks operate on 11 different frequencies. In
order to connect to even the most basic wireless network, you will
have to setup these two pieces of information, and possibly others,
before setting up things like the WNIC's IP address. Here you can see
that my ESSID is set to &#34;nest&#34; and my laptop is
transmitting at 2.432 GHz. This is all that is required to connect to
an unencrypted wireless LAN. &#40;For any of you out there expecting
to come to my house and use my unencrypted wireless, you should know
that you'll have to break a 2048-bit SSL key before the access point
will let you communicate with my LAN.&#41;
</para>

<screen>
  <prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>iwconfig wlan0 essid nest \
  freq 2.432G</userinput></screen>

<para>
The <arg>freq</arg> and <arg>channel</arg> arguments control basically
the same thing.  You only need to use one.  If you are unsure what
frequency or channel to use, Slackware can usually figure this out for
you.
</para>

<screen>
  <prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>iwconfig wlan0 essid nest \
  channel auto</userinput>
</screen>

<para>
Now Slackware will attempt to connect to the strongest access point on
the &#34;nest&#34; essid operating at any frequency.
</para>

</section>

<section id="wireless_wep">
<title>Wired Equivilant Protection (or Lack Thereof)</title>

<para>
Wireless networking is by its very nature less secure than wired
networking. Having your information travelling on the airwaves makes
it highly susceptible to interception by third parties, so over the
years a number of methods have been devised to make wireless
networking more secure.  The first was called Wired Equivilant
Protection, or WEP for short, and fell far short of its goal. If you
are still using WEP today, I encourage you to consider using WPA2 or
some other form of stronger encryption. Attacks against WEP are
trivial and take only minutes to perform. Unfortunately there are
still access points configured for WEP, and you may need to connect to
one from time to time. Connecting to WEP encrypted access points is
fairly simple, particularly if you have the key in hexidecimal
format. We'll need to pass the <arg>key</arg> argument along with the
password in hexidecimal or ASCII format. If using an ASCII password,
you'll need to prepend it with &#34;s&#59;&#34; but generally
speaking, hexidecimal format is preferred.
</para>

<screen>
<prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>iwconfig wlan0 \
  key cf80baf8bf01a160de540bfb1c</userinput>
<prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>iwconfig wlan0 \
  key s:thisisapassword</userinput>
</screen>

</section>

<section id="wireless_wpa">
<title>Wifi Protected Access</title>

<para>
Wifi Protected Access (or WPA for short) was the successor for WEP that
aimed to fix several problems with wireless encryption. Unfortunately,
WPA had some flaws as well.  An update called WPA2 offers even stronger
protection. At this time, WPA2 is supported by nearly all wireless
network cards and access points, but some older devices may only
support WEP. If you need to secure your wireless network traffic, WPA2
should be considered the minimum level of protection required.
Unfortunately, <application>iwconfig</application> is unable to setup
WPA2 encryption on its own.  For that, we need a helper daemon,
<application>wpa_supplicant</application>(8).
</para>

<para>
Unfortunately, there's no easy way to manually configure a WPA2
protected network; you'll have to edit
<filename>/etc/wpa_supplicant.conf</filename> directly with a text
editor. Here we will discuss the simplest form of WPA2 protection, the
Pre-Shared Key, or PSK for short. For details on setting up Slackware
to connect to more complicated WPA2 encrypted networks, see the man
page for <filename>wpa_supplicant.conf</filename>.
</para>

<screen>
&#35; /etc/wpa_supplicant.conf
&#35; ========================
&#35; This line enables the use of wpa_cli which is used by rc.wireless
&#35; if possible (to check for successful association)
ctrl_interface=/var/run/wpa_supplicant
&#35; By default, only root (group 0) may use wpa_cli
ctrl_interface_group=0
eapol_version=1
ap_scan=1
fast_reauth=1
&#35;country=US

&#35; WPA protected network, supply your own ESSID and WPAPSK here:
network=&#123;
  scan_ssid=1
  ssid="nest"
  key_mgmt=WPA-PSK
  psk="secret passphrase"
&#125;
</screen>

<para>
The block of text we're interested in is the network block enclosed by
curly braces.  Here we have set the ssid for the network
<varname>&#34;nest&#34;</varname>, and <varname>&#34;secret
passphrase&#34;</varname> as the PSK to be used. At this point, WPA2 is properly
configured.  You can run <application>wpa_supplicant</application> and
then obtain an IP address via DHCP or set a static address.  Of
course, this is a lot of work; there must be an easier way to do this.
</para>

<!-- not closing this yet /section -->

<section id="wireless_rcinet1conf-revisited">
<title>rc.inet1.conf revisited</title>

<para>
Welcome back to <filename>rc.inet1.conf</filename>.  You're recall
that in <xref linkend="ch_network"/> we used this configuration file
to automatically configure NICs whenever Slackware boots.  Now, we
will use it to configure wifi as well.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
    If you're using WPA2, you'll still need to setup
    <filename>wpa_supplicant.conf</filename> properly first, however.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
Recall that each NIC had a name or number that identified the variables
that correspond with it?  The same hold true for wifi NICs, only they
have even more variables due to the added complexity of wireless
networking.
</para>

<screen>
&#35; rc.inet1.conf (excert)
&#35; ======================
&#35;&#35; Example config information for wlan0.  Uncomment the lines you need and fill
&#35;&#35; in your info.  (You may not need all of these for your wireless network)
IFNAME[4]="wlan0"
IPADDR[4]=""
NETMASK[4]=""
USE_DHCP[4]="yes"
&#35;DHCP_HOSTNAME[4]="icculus-wireless"
&#35;DHCP_KEEPRESOLV[4]="yes"
&#35;DHCP_KEEPNTP[4]="yes"
&#35;DHCP_KEEPGW[4]="yes"
&#35;DHCP_IPADDR[4]=""
WLAN_ESSID[4]="nest"
&#35;WLAN_MODE[4]=Managed
&#35;WLAN_RATE[4]="54M auto"
&#35;WLAN_CHANNEL[4]="auto"
&#35;WLAN_KEY[4]="D5AD1F04ACF048EC2D0B1C80C7"
&#35;WLAN_IWPRIV[4]="set AuthMode=WPAPSK | \
&#35;   set EncrypType=TKIP | \
&#35;   set WPAPSK=96389dc66eaf7e6efd5b5523ae43c7925ff4df2f8b7099495192d44a774fda16"
WLAN_WPA[4]="wpa_supplicant"
&#35;WLAN_WPADRIVER[4]="ndiswrapper"
</screen>

<para>
When we discussed wired ethernet, each <varname>n</varname> in the
variable corresponded with the <varname>n</varname> in
<parameter>eth<emphasis>n</emphasis></parameter>.  Here however, that
no longer holds true. Notice that the variable IFNAME[4] has a value
of <varname>wlan0</varname>. It is common for wireless cards to have an interface name
other than <varname>ethn</varname> and that is reflected here.  When
<filename>rc.inet1.conf</filename> is read by the start-up scripts,
Slackware knows to apply all these options to the <varname>wlan0</varname> wifi NIC
instead of the &#40;probably non-existant&#41; eth4 wired NIC.  Many of the
other options are the same. IP address information is added in
exactly the same way we discussed for wired network cards in <xref
linkend="ch_network"/>; however, we have a lot of new variables that need
some explanation.
</para>

<para>
To begin, <varname>WLAN_ESSID[n]</varname> and
<varname>WLAN_CHANNEL[n]</varname> should be self-explainatory by now;
they refer the the essid and frequency to
use. <varname>WLAN_MODE[n]</varname> is either
<parameter>managed</parameter> or <parameter>ad-hoc</parameter>.
Anyone connecting to an access point will want to use managed mode.
<varname>WLAN_KEY[n]</varname> is the WEP key to use, if you're forced
to use WEP.  <varname>WLAN_IWPRIV[n]</varname> is a very complicated
variable that sets other variables inside itself.
<varname>WLAN_IWPRIV[n]</varname> is used for WPA2 networks.  Here you
tell Slackware what authentication mode, encryption type, and key to
use for WPA2 connections.  Please note that
<varname>WLAN_KEY[n]</varname> and <varname>WLAN_IWPRIV[n]</varname>
are mutually exclusive; you can't use both on the same interface.  If
you successfully configure all this, then Slackware will attempt to
connect to your wireless network as soon as the system boots.
</para>

<para>
But wait, that's so much work!  And what if I need to connect to
multiple wireless networks?  I take my laptop to work and school and
need to seemlessly setup those wireless connections as soon as one is
within range.  Doing things this way is simply too much work.  You're
absolutely correct.
</para>

</section> <!-- closing rc.inet1.conf revisited -->

</section> <!-- closing WPA discussion -->

<section id="wireless_wicd">
  <title>wicd</title>

<para>
Introducing <application>wicd</application>(8), the premier wired and
wireless network connection manager for the laptop user on the go.
Pronounced &#34;wicked&#34;, <application>wicd</application> is capable of
storing information for any number of wireless networks you need and
connecting to them with a simple command or the click of a mouse.
<application>wicd</application> is not part of the default Slackware
installation at this time, as it interferes somewhat with the normal
way of configuring network adapters, but you can find it in the
<filename>&#47;extra</filename> directory of your Slackware install disks
or at your favorite mirror. <application>wicd</application> is both a
network connection daemon and a graphical application for configuring
networks.  The CLI isn't forgotten either, as
<application>wicd-curses</application>(8) is every bit as powerful as
the traditional GUI front-end.  In order to use
<application>wicd</application>, you will need to disable support for
any interfaces you have in <filename>rc.inet1.conf</filename> first.
</para>

<screen>
&#35; rc.inet1.conf
&#35; =============
&#35; Config information for eth0:
IPADDR[0]=&#34;&#34;
NETMASK[0]=&#34;&#34;
USE_DHCP[0]=&#34;no&#34;
DHCP_HOSTNAME[0]=&#34;&#34;
&#35; Default gateway IP address:
GATEWAY=&#34;&#34;
</screen>

<para>
Now we can install <application>wicd</application>, setup the daemon to
run on system boot-up, and begin using a more friendly application.
</para>

<screen><prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>installpkg &#47;path&#47;to&#47;extra&#47;wicd&#47;wicd-1.6.2.1-1.txz</userinput>
<prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>chmod +x &#47;etc&#47;rc.d&#47;rc.wicd</userinput>
<prompt>darkstar:~&#35; </prompt><userinput>&#47;etc&#47;rc.d&#47;rc.wicd start</userinput>
</screen>

<para>
If you're predominately using the console, simply run
<application>wicd-curses</application> from your command line. If
instead, you are using a graphical desktop provided by
<application>X</application>, you can start the graphical front-end
from either the KDE or XFCE menu.
</para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata
	  fileref="./img/wicd.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
      <phrase>The wicd interface</phrase>
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

<para>
  Optionally, you could manually run
<application>wicd-client</application>(1) from a terminal or <application>run
dialogue</application>.
</para>

<para>
  On the graphical front-end, options for different networks are
  available via the <guibutton>Preferences</guibutton> button adjacent
  to the ESSID listed. In the terminal client, the same options can be
  reached by highlighting the ESSID you wish to use and
  pressing the right arrow key, which opens a configuration page for
  that network.
</para>

</section> <!-- closing wicd section -->

</chapter>